I'm excited to introduce
Dr. Kristine Dennis,
our new Senior Research Scientist
who has been researching and
scripting new video topics and,
as you'll hear today,
narrating some as well.
In this video, Kristine
delves into the association
between vegetarian diets and
hypospadias birth defects
to see if it holds up in
the light of new research.
"Pesticide Exposure and Hypospadias
Birth Defects in Vegetarians"
In 2000, a study found that a
vegetarian diet during pregnancy
was associated with hypospadias,
a specific birth defect
of the penis.
The authors suggested
that it may be due
to the greater exposure
to phytoestrogens,
which are found in soy foods.
But if you look globally,
while there is
an extraordinarily
high prevalence
in North America and Europe,
it's extremely low
in a country like Japan,
which has the highest per capita
soy intake in the world.
In fact, in Japan,
a low maternal intake
of soy phytoestrogens
has been associated with
elevated risk of hypospadias,
so, if anything,
soy may be protective.
If soy foods aren't
the hormone disrupters,
what in a vegetarian diet
might be?
Well, occupational
exposure to pesticides
is associated with higher risk,
so, might low-level pesticide
exposure among those eating
more fruits and vegetables--
like vegetarians--
help explain it?
If you randomize people
to a more plant-based
Mediterranean diet,
you see a large increase
in the amount of pesticides
flowing through their body,
though, of course,
if you put them
on a Mediterranean diet
with organic fruits
and vegetables,
you see a 90 percent drop
in pesticide exposure.
So, does organic food
consumption during pregnancy
reduce hypospadias risk?
Apparently so,
cutting the odds about in half,
particularly when
it comes to choosing
organic vegetables and dairy,
though the only other study
to look at organic food choices
and hypospadias
found the risk associated
just with conventional
high-fat dairy products.
It isn't all or nothing.
Even if only two thirds
of your produce is organic,
that can significantly reduce
pesticide exposure,
but the benefits of consuming
conventionally grown produce
likely outweigh any possible
risks from pesticide exposure,
so, concerns over
ingesting pesticides
should never discourage
fruit and vegetable intake.
In the United States alone,
if you add up all
of the fatal cancers, strokes,
heart attacks, and other deaths
that could have been averted
simply by eating
more fruits and vegetables,
it comes out to nearly
450,000 deaths every year.
That's how powerful
produce can be.
But might one of the downsides
be this hypospadias risk?
Despite their high
plant consumption,
vegetarians may be less exposed
to conventional pesticides,
but that's because
of their greater propensity
to choose organic produce.
Now, the researchers only
considered the pesticides
in plant foods,
not animal products,
and even for
conventional insecticides,
animal products are
main contributors to exposure.
Additionally,
persistent pesticides,
such as organochlorine
pesticides like DDT,
are concentrated in fish,
other meats, and dairy,
so it's no surprise
that the blood of
strictly plant-based eaters
ends up significantly
less polluted.
It may not just be from the
lower level of intake, though;
high fiber diets can bulk up the
stool and glom on to pesticides
and flush them away.
In the end, the hypospadias
issue may be another example
of the stroke scare.
Dr. Greger did a whole series
covering potential explanations
why a study had found higher
stroke rates among vegetarians,
but then, half a dozen
other studies found
lower rates of stroke,
if anything, across the board.
The original hypospadias study
looked at about 50 cases.
Twelve years later,
a study that looked
at 1,250 cases was published
and found zero increased risk
among vegetarian mothers.